Now remember, keep your shoulders back.
자, 꼭 어깨를 똑바로 해야 해
Okay. Put your arm around your brother.
That's it.
자, 형 어깨에 팔을 올리고
그렇지
That's it, right there.
Okay, one more.
좋아, 한 번 더
죽은 시인의 사회
.
자, 이제 다시 한 번 해보자
Now, just to review.
교장 선생님 앞에 갈 때까지
You're going to follow
along with the procession...
행렬을 따라 가도록 해라
until you get to the headmaster.
그때, 교장 선생님이 너에게
At that point, he will indicate to you
to light the candles of the boys.
학생들의 촛불에 불을 켜도록
하라고 지시할 거야
자, 학생들, 조용히 해요
All right, boys, let's settle down.
교기 올리고
Banners up!
Ladies and gentlemen, boys,
the light of knowledge.
학부모 및 학생 여러분
지식의 촛불입니다
One hundred years ago,
in 1859...
100년 전, 1859년에도
41명의 소년들이 여기 앉아서
41 boys sat in this room...
and were asked the same question...
학기를 시작하는 데 있어서
여러분을 반기는 똑같은
질문을 받았습니다
that now greets you
at the start of each semester.
Gentlemen, what are the four pillars?
여러분, 4개의 교훈은
무엇 입니까?
Tradition, honor...
전통, 명예, 규율, 최고
discipline, excellence.
웰튼 아카데미가 설립된 해에
ln her first year...
Welton Academy graduated five students.
5명의 학생이 졸업했고
Last year, we graduated 51...
작년에는 51명의 학생이
졸업을 했습니다
그중 75%가 넘는 학생들이
and more than 75% of those...
아이비리그에 진학했습니다
went on to the lvy League.
This, this kind of accomplishment...
이런, 이런 훌륭한 업적은
우리 학교가
is the result...
열성적으로 가르친 원칙들의
결과입니다
of fervent dedication to the principles
taught here.
그것은 곧 학부모님들의
자제 분들을
This is why you parents
have been sending us your sons.
이곳에 보내는 이유이기도 하며
이곳이 미국에서 최고가는
대학 진학 예비 학교인가
This is why we are the best
preparatory school in the United States.
하는 이유인 것입니다
As you know...
아시다시피, 우리의 존경스런
our beloved Mr. Portius of the
English Department retired last term.
포티우스 영어 교사가
지난 학기 퇴직하셔서
존 키팅 선생님을 그의 후임
으로 소개합니다
You will have the opportunity later to
meet his replacement Mr. John Keating...
키팅 선생님은 우리 학교의
우수한 졸업생이셨고
himself an honors graduate
of this school.
And who, for the past several years...
지난 수년간
교편을 잡으신 분입니다
has been teaching at the highly regarded
Chester School in London.
런던의 명문 체스터 고교에서
- Richard, you forgot your bag.
- Hi, Johnny. Hey, how you doin'?
와 주셔서 감사합니다
Glad you could come by.
항상 그랬지만, 훌륭한 입학
식이었습니다
-Thrilling ceremony as usual, Dr. Nolan.
-You've been away too long.
오랜만입니다
안녕하세요, 교장 선생님
- Hello, Dr. Nolan.
- Good to have you.
- This is our youngest, Todd.
우리 막내 토드예요
Mr. Anderson, you have
some big shoes to fill, young man.
앤더슨 군, 자네에게
기대가 크다네
자네형은 훌륭한 학생
이었다네
- Your brother was one of our finest.
- Thank you.
감사합니다
멋진 환영식 이었어요
- Lovely ceremony.
- Thank you. l'm so glad you liked it.
감사합니다, 그렇게 말씀해
주시니 영광입니다
- Gale.
- Tom.
- 게일
- 존
다시 만나서 기쁘네
- Good to see you again.
- Hello, Mr. Nolan.
안녕하세요, 교장 선생님
- Neil, we expect great things
from you this year.
- Thank you, sir.
닐, 올해에도 자네에게
기대가 크다네
감사합니다
- Well, he won't disappoint us.
Right, Neil?
- l'll do my best, sir.
우릴 실망시키지 않겠지?
최선을 다하겠습니다
힘내야지, 내 아들
- Come on, son.
- Chin up.
- Okay.
용기를 내야지
- Chin up.
- No tears now.
- l don't want to go here.
- Honey, l love you.
아빠, 이제 그만 울거라
- l'll walk you over.
- There, there. Do your lessons.
만나러 올께
이런, 공부 열심히 해야 한다
이봐! 우리가 룸메이트라고
하던데, 난 닐 페리야
Hey. l hear we're gonna be roommates.
- l'm Neil Perry.
- l'm Todd Anderson.
난 토드 앤더슨이야
왜 여기로 전학 왔지?
- Why'd you leave Balincrest?
- My brother went here.
우리형이 여길 다녔어
오, 네가 그 유명한
앤더슨이구나
Oh, so you're that Anderson!
This is for his sinuses.
And, oh, if he, if he can't, uh,
swallow, you give him one of these.
여기 천식 약입니다
그리고, 어, 삼키기가 힘들다고
하면, 이걸 주십시오
- And if he has trouble breathing,
you give him--
- All right, fine.
호흡장애가 있으면, 이걸
주시구요
아, 알았어요
And, oh, did you remember
your vaporizer? And the vapor--
그리고....오! 가습기 가져왔지?
네, 방에 뒀어요
그리고, 가습기는....
닐, 잘 있었어?
- Hey, how's it going, Neil?
- Come down here.
- Neil? Study group tonight?
- Yeah, sure.
- 닐, 오늘밤에 스터디 그룹 있니?
- 그래
항상 그랬던 것처럼 말야
Business as usual, huh?
Hey, l heard you got the new kid.
이봐, 새로 온 학생과 같이
쓴다며, 멍청이 같이 생겼던데
Looks like a stiff!
Oops.
이런
이봐, 카메론 말은 신경 쓰지마
원래 입이 거친 녀석이니까
Listen. Don't mind Cameron. He's, uh,
born with his foot in his mouth.
Know what l mean?
무슨 말인지 알지?
Rumor has it,
you did summer school.
너 여름 학기에 다녔다는
소문이 있던데
Yep. Chemistry.
My father thought l should get ahead.
그래, 화학
아버지께서 내가 예습을 해야
한다고 해서
네 여름 방학은 어땠니?
- How was your summer, Slick?
- Keen.
멋졌지
믹스, 문 닫아
- Meeks, door, closed.
- Yes, sir!
그럽죠
여러분? 4개 교훈이 뭐지?
익살, 공포, 타락, 배설
Gentlemen, what are the four pillars?
Travesty, horror, decadence, excrement.
자, 스터디 그룹 얘긴데, 믹스는
라틴어에서 최고고
Okay, study group.
Meeks aced Latin.
l didn't quite flunk English.
나는 영어를 잘해
그러니까, 원한다면 스터디
그룹을 할 수 있어
So, if you want,
we got our study group.
Sure. Cameron asked me too.
Anyone mind including him?
물론이지, 카메론도
하고 싶다고 했어
그가 끼는게 싫은 사람?
특기가 뭔데? 아부하는 거?
What's his specialty? Bootlicking?
그 앤 네 룸메이트잖아
- Um, he's your roommate.
- That's not my fault!
그건 내 잘못이 아니지
오, 미안해, 난 스테판 믹스야
Uh, l'm sorry.
My name is Stephen Meeks.
- Oh, this is Todd Anderson.
- Nice to meet you.
오, 여긴 토드 앤더슨
만나서 반가워
반가워
찰리 달튼이야
Charlie Dalton.
난 녹스 오버스트리트야
Knox Overstreet.
토드 형이 제프리 앤더슨이래
Todd's brother was Jeffrey Anderson.
오, 그래
그랬었군
- Oh, yeah, sure!
- Ooh, wow.
전교에서 1등으로 졸업했고
전국 우등생 상을 받았지
- Valedictorian, National Merit Scholar.
- Oh, well!
오, 그래, 지옥 학교에 온걸
환영해
Welcome to Hell-ton!
lt's every bit as tough as they say
unless you're a genius like Meeks.
여긴 소문대로 정말 힘든 곳이야
믹스 같은 천재야 괜찮지만
아부하는 거야, 그래야 내가
라틴어 공부를 도와주거든
He flatters me.
That's why l help him with Latin.
영어랑 삼각함수도
And English, and trig.
들어오세요, 아버지
가신 줄 알았는데요
lt's open.
Father, l thought you'd gone.
- Mr. Perry, sir.
- Keep your seats, fellas.
Keep your seats.
페리씨, 페리씨, 페리씨
모두들 앉아 있어라, 앉아
닐, 방금 교장 선생님과
얘길 했는데
Neil, l've just spoken to Mr. Nolan.
넌 이번 학기에 과외활동이
너무 많으니까
l think that you're taking
too many extracurricular activities
this semester.
졸업연감 일은 그만 둬라
And l've decided
that you should drop school annual.
하지만 전 부편집장인걸요
-But l'm the assistant editor this year.
-Well, l'm, l'm sorry, Neil.
미안하게 생각한다
하지만, 아버지,
그건 말도 안되는.....
- But, Father, l can't.
lt wouldn't be fair.
- Fellas?
여러분, 잠깐 단둘이
할 얘기가 있다
Would you excuse us for a moment?
사람들 있는데서 나한테
반항하지마, 알겠니?
- Don't you ever dispute me in public!
Do you understand?
- Father, l wasn't disputing you--
아버지, 전....
의대를 졸업하게 되면
그땐 네 마음대로 해
After you've finished medical school
and you're on your own, then you can
do as you damn well please.
하지만 그때 까진 내가 시키는
대로해라 알겠니?
But until then, you do as l tell you.
ls that clear?
네, 죄송합니다
Yes, sir. l'm sorry.
어머니가 너한테 얼마나 큰
기대를 하시는지 알지?
You know how much this means
to your mother, don't you?
Yes, sir.
네, 아시잖아요, 항상 제가
너무 흥분해서 그러는 거
You know me.
l'm always taking on too much.
그래, 착하지, 내 아들
Well, that's my boy.
잘 들어라, 필요한 게 있으면
언제든지 연락해
Now, listen. You need anything,
you let us know, huh?
네
Yes, sir.
왜 아버지는 네가 하고 싶은
대로 놔두지 않으시지?
Why doesn't he let you do
what you want?
Yeah, Neil, tell him off.
lt couldn't get any worse.
그래, 닐, 한번 거역해 봐
더 나아질지 아니
그것 좋지, 너희들 거역하는
것처럼 말이니?
Oh, that's rich! Like you guys tell
your parents off, Mr. Future Lawyer
and Mr. Future Banker?
미래 변호사님, 은행장님?
알았어, 우리도 다를 게 없어
Okay, so l don't like it
any more than you do.
아버지한테 어떻게 하라고 하지마
너희들도 다 똑같으니까
Well, just don't tell me how to talk
to my father. You guys are the same way.
All right, all right. Jesus.
So what are you gonna do then?
알았어, 알았다구
이제 어떡할거야?
말씀하신 대로
연감 일을 그만 둬야지
What l have to do.
Drop the annual.
그래, 너무 속상해 하지마
Well, l wouldn't lose too much sleep
over it. lt's just a bunch of jerks
trying to impress Nolan.
교장 선생님에게 잘 보일
려는 애들일 뿐이니까
됐어, 이제 아무렇지도 않아
l don't care.
l don't give a damn about any of it.
8시에 내 방에서 라틴어
공부할까?
Well, uh, Latin, 8:00 in my room?
그래
- Yes.
- l guess so.
토드? 너도 같이 와
- Todd, you're welcome to join us.
- Yeah, come along, pal.
그래, 같이하자
고마와
Thanks.
조용히들 내려가라, 이놈들!
Slow down, boys!
조용히 내려가, 이 사춘기
괴물들아
Slow down, you horrible
phalanx of pubescence!
Pick three laboratory experiments
from the project list...
프로젝트 목록중 실험 3개를
선택해서 5주마다
and report on them
every five weeks.
실험경과 보고서 제출하고
1장 끝부분 20문제는
내일까지 하도록 해
The first 20 questions at the end
of chapter one are due tomorrow.
아그리콜람
- Agricolam.
아그리콜라
- Agricola.
아그리콜래
- Agricolae.
아그리콜라름
- Agricolarum.
아그리콜리름
아그리콜리스
- Agricolis.
아그리콜라스
- Agricolas.
아그리콜리스
- Agricolis.
다시 한 번, 아그리콜라
- Again, please. Agricola.
- Agricola.
Your study of trigonometry...
삼각함수론은 정확성이 가장
중요하다
requires absolute precision.
누구라도 숙제를 제출하지 않은
학생이 있다면
Anyone failing to turn in
any homework assignment...
최종점수에서 1점을 감점
당할 것이다.
will be penalized one point
off their final grade.
날 시험해 보려고 하지
않기를 바란다
Let me urge you now
not to test me on this point.
Hey, Spaz! Spaz!
이봐, 스패즈! 스패즈!
Brain damage!
어서 와
Well, come on!
어서 가자구
- Let's go.
- Let's go, guys.
오, 선장, 나의 선장이여
"O Captain! My captain!"
이게 누구 시에 나오는지
아는 사람?
Who knows where that comes from?
아무도?
Anybody.
전혀 모르겠나?
Not a clue?
에이브라함 링컨을 찬양한
월트 휘트먼의 시야
lt's from a poem by Walt Whitman
about Mr. Abraham Lincoln.
나를 키팅 선생님이라고 불러
도 좋고 아니면 대담하게
Now, in this class,
you can either call me Mr. Keating...
or if you're slightly more daring
O Captain, my Captain.
오, 선장, 나의 선장님이라고
불러도 된다
Now let me dispel a few rumors,
so they don't fester into facts.
자, 소문거리가 되는것은
싫으니 머리말을 꺼내겠다
그래, 나도 역시
이 지옥 학교에서 살아남았다
Yes, l, too, attended Hell-ton
and have survived.
그리고 그 당시엔 나도 지금처럼
지적인 사람이 아니었다
And, no, at that time l was not
the mental giant you see before you.
45kg밖에 안 나가는
약골에 불과했고
l was the intellectual equivalent
of a 98-pound weakling.
해변을 거닐때면 사람들은 나에게
바이런 시집을 던지곤 했지
l would go to the beach, and people
would kick copies of Byron in my face.
Now...
자, 핏츠, 이름이 좀 불행하군
Mr. Pitts.
That's a rather unfortunate name.
Mr. Pitts, where are you?
핏츠군, 어딨나?
Mr. Pitts, will you open your hymnal
to page 542?
핏츠군, 찬송가의
542페이지를 펴고
거기에 나온 시의 첫 구절을
읽어 봐
Read the first stanza
of the poem you find there.
'시간을 버는 천사에게'
말인가요?
- "To The Virgins to Make Much of Time"?
- Yes. That's the one.
그래, 바로 그거야
어울리는 시지?
Somewhat appropriate, isn't it?
시간이 있을 때 장미 봉우리를
거두라....
"Gather ye rosebuds while ye may,
old time is still a-flying...
시간은 흘러
and this same flower that smiles today,
tomorrow will be dying."
오늘 핀 꽃이 내일이면
질 것이다
고맙네, 핏츠군. 시간이 있을 때
장미 봉우리를 거두라
Thank you, Mr. Pitts.
"Gather ye rosebuds
while ye may."
이걸 라틴말로 표현하자면
'카르페 티엠'이지
The Latin term for that sentiment
is carpe diem.
자, 그게 무슨 뜻인지 아는 사람?
Now who knows what that means?
Carpe diem.
That's seize the day.
'카르페 디엠' 그것은 현재를
즐기라는 말입니다
- Very good, Mr.--
- Meeks.
좋네, 이름이.....?
믹스입니다, 믹스군
Meeks. Another unusual name.
또 이상한 이름이군
Seize the day.
현재를 즐겨라, 시간이 있을 때
장미 봉우리를 거두라
"Gather ye rosebuds
while ye may."
왜 시인이 이런 말을 썼지?
- Why does the writer use these lines?
- Because he's in a hurry.
시인이 성질이 급하니까요?
No! Ding!
아니, 땡, 대답에 응해준건 고맙네
Thank you for playing anyway.
왜냐면 우리는 반드시
죽기 때문이지
Because we are food for worms, lads.
Because, believe it or not,
each and every one of us in this room...
믿거나 말거나
여기 있는 우리 각자
is one day going to stop breathing...
모두는 언젠가는 숨이 멎고
차가워 져서 죽게되지
turn cold, and die.
이쪽으로 와서 과거의
얼굴들을 지켜봐라
l would like you to step forward
over here...
and peruse some of the faces
from the past.
여러 번 이방을 왔어도
You've walked past them many times,
but l don't think
you've really looked at them.
유심히 본 적은 없었을 거야
They're not that different from you,
are they?
너희와 별로 다르지 않을 거야
그렇지?
머리모양도 같고, 너희
처럼 젊고 패기만만하고
Same haircuts...
full of hormones just like you.
lnvincible just like you feel.
너희처럼 세상을 그들 손에 넣어
The world is their oyster.
They believe they're destined
for great things just like many of you.
위대한 일을 할거라 믿고
그들의 눈도 너희들처럼
희망에 가득 차 있다
Their eyes are full of hope
just like you.
하지만 그 당시 그들의 능력을
Did they wait until it was too late
to make from their lives...
even one iota of what
they were capable?
발휘할 시기를 놓친 것일까?
왜냐하면 이 사람들은 죽어서
땅에 묻혀 있는지 오래다
Because you see, gentlemen, these boys
are now fertilizing daffodils.
하지만 여러분들이 잘 들어보면
그들의 속삭임이 들릴 것이다
But if you listen real close...
you can hear them whisper
their legacy to you.
자, 귀를 기울여 봐, 들리나?
Go on, lean in.
Listen.
Do you hear it?
Carpe.
카르페
들리나?
Hear it?
카르페
Carpe.
카르페디엠
Carpe diem.
Seize the day, boys.
현재를 즐겨라
Make your lives extraordinary.
인생을 독특하게 살아라
이상했어
- That was weird.
- But different.
하지만 특별했잖아
난 등골이 오싹했어
Spooky, if you ask me.
Think he'll test us on that stuff?
그게 시험에 나오는 걸까?
오, 카메론, 겨우 그 정도밖에
안되니?
Oh, come on, Cameron,
don't you get anything?
뭘? 왜!
What? What?
Let's go, boys. Hustle up in here.
That means you, Dalton.
얘들아, 어서 서둘러
너한테 하는 말이야, 달튼
얘들아, 오늘 밤, 삼각함수
공부할 사람?
All right, who's up
for our trig study group tonight, guys?
- Sure.
- Me.
- Me, me, me.
나, 나도, 나도, 뭐?
Well, l can't make it, guys.
l have to have dinner
at the Danburrys' house tonight.
난 안돼, 댄버리 가에서 저녁
식사가 있거든
댄버리가라고? 그게 누군데?
- Ooh, not the Danburrys.
- Who are the Danburrys?
중요한 선배야
어떻게 알게 됐니?
Big alums!
How'd you swing that?
아버지 친구 분이야
90살 정도 되셨겠지
Friends of my dad's. They're probably
in their 90s or something.
우
- Hey.
- Sounds great, doesn't it?
- Anything's better than Hell-ton hash.
이봐, 좋겠다, 기숙사 음식보다
는 백 배 낫겠지
- Knox.
- l'll second that.
- Yeah, well, we'll see.
그렇겠지
이봐, 오늘 밤
스터디 그룹에 올래?
Hey! Want to come
to the study group tonight?
어, 아니, 아니, 난 역사
공부를 해야 해
Wha-- Uh, no. No. l've, l-l've got
some history l want to do.
네 맘대로 해
Suit yourself.
오버스트리트, 준비됐나?
Ready, Overstreet?
네
Ready to go, sir.
쳇트, 네가 나가 주겠니?
- Chet, can you get that?
- l can't, Mom.
- l'll get it.
내가 나갈께요
어떻게 오셨죠?
Can l help you?
안녕하세요, 전 녹스
오버스트리트이고
Hi. K-Knox Overstreet.
Uh, Dr. Hager.
이분은 헤이거 박사님이십니다
안녕하세요
Hi.
- This is the Danburrys', right?
- Are, are you here to see Chet?
여기가 댄버리가 맞죠?
쳇트 만나러 오셨나요?
- Mrs. Danburry?
- No.
댄버리 부인이세요?
아니에요
l'm sorry. Thank you, Chris.
l'm Mrs. Danburry.
죄송합니다, 고맙다, 크리스
제가 댄버리 부인이에요
- You must be Knox.
- Yes.
어, 네가 녹스구나
네
9시에 데리러 오세요
자, 어서 들어와라
Back by 9:00?
Please, come on in.
크리스! 뭐해!
- Chris, come on. What are you doing?
- Chet, l'm coming.
쳇트, 지금 가요
- Knox! How are you? Joe Danburry.
- Nice to meet you, sir.
녹스, 잘 있었니?
난 존 댄 버리네
만나뵈서 반갑습니다
이런, 아버지를 참 많이 닮았군
아버지는 잘 계신가?
Well, he's the splitting image
of his father, isn't he?
- How is he? Come on in.
- He's great. He just did
a big case for G.M.
어서 들어오게
크리스
최근 GM사 소송을 치르셨어요
Yeah, l know where you're headed.
Like father, like son, huh?
자네가 뭐가 될 건지 알겠군
부전자전 이야
- Ooh, is that close!
- Yes!
- Bishop to queen six.
좋았어!
주교가 여왕에게...
또 할래?
- Another game?
- What do you mean?
- Boo!
벅!
Replace, uh, these numbers here with X--
For X and Y.
이 숫자들을 x, y 로 대치
시켜봐
당연하지
- Of course.
- Of course. So what's the problem?
잘 알면서 뭘 묻는 거야?
내가 할수 있겠니?
Do you think l can get in there?
You've been hogging it all day.
하루 종일 뭉게잖아
Look, l didn't take my hand
off of it, okay?
저녁 어땠니?
- How was dinner?
- Huh?
저녁 어땠냐고?
How was dinner?
끔찍했어
Terrible.
불쾌하고
- Awful.
- What? What happened?
왜? 무슨 일 있었어?
오늘 밤, 난 내 인생에서 제일
예쁜 소녀를 만났어
Tonight...
l met the most beautiful girl
l have ever seen in my entire life.
- Are you crazy? What's wrong with that?
- She's practically engaged.
제정신이야? 그게 어쨌다는 거야?
그 소녀는 쳇트 덴베리의
약혼자야
To Chet Danburry.
- The guy could eat a football.
- Too bad.
그 녀석은 축구 선수잖아
안됐다
안됐다구? 그 이상이라고
이건 비극이야
Too bad? lt's worse than too bad, Pitts.
lt's a tragedy.
그 아름다운 소녀가 그런
바보를 사랑하다니
A girl this beautiful
in love with such a jerk?
예쁜 애들은 바보를
사랑하기 마련이라고
All the good ones go for jerks.
You know that.
잊어버려, 삼각함수 책이나 펴고
5번 문제 풀어 봐
Yeah, forget her. Open your trig book
and try and figure out problem five.
l can't just forget her, Cameron.
And l certainly can't think about trig!
그녀가 자꾸 아른거리는데
삼각함수가 눈에 들어오겠니?
We got it!
신호가 잡혔다!
All right, gentlemen, five minutes.
Let's go.
자, 여러분, 5분 남았다
어서 가자
- Did you see her naked?
- Very funny, Dalton.
그 여자 나체는 봤어?
장난치지마, 달톤
That wouldn't be a, uh, radio
in your lap, would it, Mr. Pitts?
자네 무릎에 있는 게, 어
라디오는 아니겠지, 핏츠군?
네, 과학 실험중인
레이더입니다
No, sir.
A science experiment.
Radar.
여러분, 21페이지에 있는
서문을 펴 봐라
Gentlemen, open your texts
to page 21 of the introduction.
페리군, 서문을 한 번 읽어
보겠나? 제목 말이야
Mr. Perry, will you read the opening
paragraph of the preface...
'시의 이해' 말이야
entitled "Understanding Poetry"?
'시의 이해' 에반스 프리차드
문학박사 저
"Understanding Poetry
by Dr. J. Evans Pritchard, Ph.D.
'시를 완전히 이해하기 위해서는
To fully understand poetry,
we must first be fluent...
with its meter, rhyme
and figures of speech.
운율, 음조, 비유를 이해하라
그리고 2가지 질문을 하라
Then ask two questions:
One, how artfully has the objective
of the poem been rendered?
첫째, 대상의 예술적 표현도
두 번째, 대상의 중요도이다
첫째는 시의 완성도 측정이며
And two, how important
is that objective?
Question one rates
the poem's perfection.
두 번째는 중요도의 판단이다
Question two rates its importance.
이 두 질문에 대한 답이 나오면
And once these questions
have been answered...
시의 위대함이 쉽게 판별된다
determining the poem's greatness
becomes a relatively simple matter.
시의 완성도를 가로축에 놓고
lf the poem's score for perfection is
plotted on the horizontal of a graph...
중요도를 세로축에 놓으면
and its importance
is plotted on the vertical...
그 시의 위대함은 완성도와
중요도의 영역이다
then calculating
the total area of the poem...
yields the measure of its greatness.
A sonnet by Byron might score high...
바이런의 시는 중요도는 높지만
완성도는 겨우 보통을 넘는다
on the vertical,
but only average on the horizontal.
A Shakespearean sonnet on the,
on the other hand would...
반면에 세익스피어의 14행시는
score high both horizontally
and vertically...
두 가지 면에서 모두
높다고 볼 수 있다
yielding a massive total area...
thereby revealing the poem
to be truly great.
고로 매우 범위가 넓으므로
실로 위대한 시가 되는 것이다
이 책에 수록된 시를 읽는 동안
이 평가 방법을 연습하도록 해라
As you proceed through the poetry in
this book, practice this rating method.
이러한 방법으로 시를 평가하는
능력이 길러지면 시를 통해 얻는
As your ability to evaluate poems
in this manner grows...
기쁨과 이해도 깊어질 것이다
so will, so will your enjoyment
and understanding of poetry."
쓰레기!!
Excrement.
그게 J. 에반스 프릿차드에
대한 나의 견해이다
That's what l think of
Mr. J. Evans Pritchard.
재는 것이 아니다
We're not laying pipe.
We're talking about poetry.
시를 어떻게
아메리칸 탑 텐처럼
평가할 수 있겠나?
How can you describe poetry
like American Bandstand?
'오, 난 바이런 시는 42점짜리라
안 좋아해'
"Oh, l like Byron. l give him a 42,
but l can't dance to it."
자, 이제 그 장을 찢어 버려라
어서, 몽땅 찢어 버려
Now, l want you to rip out that page.
Go on. Rip out the entire page.
You heard me. Rip it out.
안 들리나. 어서 찢어내라구
어서. 찢어 버리라니까
Rip it out!
Go on. Rip it out!
Thank you, Mr. Dalton.
고맙네, 달튼군
Gentlemen, tell you what.
Don't just tear out that page,
tear out the entire introduction.
여러분. 그 페이지 말고도
서문 전체를 찢어 버려라
l want it gone. History.
Leave nothing of it.
서문은 오늘로 끝이니 완전히
찢어 내 버려라, 찢어 내버려!
Rip it out! Rip!
Be gone, J. Evans Pritchard, Ph.D.
프리챠드 박사님을 없애거라
Rip. Shred. Tear.
Rip it out!
찢어 내버려, 프리챠드 박사
님을 쫓아내는 소리가 듣고 싶다
l want to hear nothing but ripping
of Mr. Pritchard.
찢어 내서 화장지로
써야겠다
We'll perforate it,
put it on a roll.
이건 성경이 아니야
이런다고 지옥에 안가
lt's not the Bible.
You're not gonna go to hell for this.
Go on. Make a clean tear.
l want nothing left of it.
어서 찢어, 깨끗이 찢어 버려라
하나도 남김 없이
- We shouldn't be doing this.
- Rip! Rip! Rip!
책을 찢어내면 안돼
찢어! 찢어! 찢어버려
찢어내 버려!
Rip it out! Rip!
Rip it out!
도대체 무슨 짓들이지?
What the hell is going on here?
찢는 소리가 안 들려!
- l don't hear enough rips!
- Mr. Keating.
키팅 선생님
맥칼리스터 선생님
Mr. McAllister.
죄송합니다, 여기 계신 줄
몰랐습니다
l'm sorry.
l, l didn't know you were here.
여기 있습니다
l am. Ah.
So you are.
그렇군요, 실례했습니다
Excuse me.
Keep ripping, gentlemen!
자, 계속 찢어라
This is a battle, a war.
이건 전투요 전쟁이다
지면 마음과 영혼이 다친다
And the casualties could be
your hearts and souls.
고맙네, 달튼군
Thank you, Mr. Dalton.
우수한 학생들한테 시를
측정하게 만들다니, 안되지!
Armies of academics going forward
measuring poetry.
No! We'll not have that here.
No more Mr. J. Evans Pritchard.
여기 내버려둬선 안돼! J
에반스 프리챠드여 사라져라
여러분
Now, my class, you will learn
to think for yourselves again.
이제 여러분은 생각하는 법을
다시 배우게 될 거야
여러분은 말과
언어의 맛을 배우게 될 거야
You will learn to savor
words and language.
No matter what anybody tells you...
누가 무슨 말을 하든지
말과 언어는 세상을
바꿔놓을 수 있다
words and ideas can change the world.
핏츠군은 19세기 문학과
의대에 가는 것과는
Now l see that look in Mr. Pitts' eye,
like 19th century literature...
has nothing to do with going
to business school or medical school.
아무 상관없다 여기는군
그런가?
Right? Maybe.
홉킨스군, 자네도 같은 생각
인가 보군
Mr. Hopkins, you may agree with him,
thinking...
"Yes, we should simply study
our Mr. Pritchard
and learn our rhyme and meter...
그래, 프리차드씨의 말대로
음조와 운율을 배워서
and go quietly about the business
of achieving other ambitions."
다른 야망을 달성하는 일을
하면 된다고 생각하지만
비밀을 하나 얘기해 주지
l've a little secret for you.
Huddle up.
가까이 모여라! 가까이 모여!
Huddle up!
We don't read and write poetry
because it's cute.
시가 아름다워서 읽고 쓰는
것이 아니다
We read and write poetry because
we are members of the human race...
인류의 일원이기 때문에 시를
읽고 쓰는 것이다
인류는 열정으로 가득 차 있어
의학, 법률, 경제, 기술 따위는
and the human race
is filled with passion.
And medicine, law, business,
engineering...
삶을 유지하는데 필요해
these are noble pursuits
and necessary to sustain life.
But poetry, beauty...
하지만 시와 미, 낭만, 사랑은
삶의 목적인 거야
romance, love...
these are what we stay alive for.
To quote from Whitman...
휘트만의 시를 인용하자면
"O me, O life of the questions
of these recurring...
'오, 나여! 오 생명이여!
수없이 던지는 이 의문!
of the endless trains
of the faithless...
믿음 없는 자들로 이어지는 도시
바보들로 넘쳐흐르는 도시
of cities filled with the foolish.
아름다움을 어디서 찾을까?
What good amid these
O me, O life?"
오, 나여, 오 생명이여! 대답은
한가지: 네가 거기에 있다는 것
Answer:
that you are here.
생명과 존재가 있다는 것
화려한 연극은 계속되고
That life exists,
and identity.
너 또한 한 편의 시가 된다는 것.'
That the powerful play goes on,
and you may contribute a verse.
'화려한 연극은 계속되고 너
또한 한 편의 시가 된다는 것'
That the powerful play goes on...
and you may contribute a verse.
여러분의 시는 어떤 것이 될까?
What will your verse be?
우리가 섭취할 음식이 하느님의
뜻대로 우리를 위대하게 만드소서
For what we are about to receive...
may the Lord make us truly grateful.
아멘
Amen.
-Quite an interesting class
you gave today, Mr. Keating.
-Sorry if l shocked you, Mr. McAllister.
오늘 수업 참 재미있더군요
키팅 선생님
놀라게 해 드렸다면
죄송합니다
Oh, there's no need to apologize.
lt was very fascinating,
misguided though it was.
사과할 필요는 없소, 방향은
틀렸어도 사로잡을 만 했소
그렇게 생각하십니까?
You think so?
학생들을 예술가가 되도록
부추기는 건 위험한 일이요
You take a big risk by encouraging them
to become artists, John.
그들 자신이 위대한 렘브란트나
셰익 스피어, 모짜르트같은
When they realize that they're not
Rembrandts, Shakespeares or Mozarts,
they'll hate you for it.
예술가가 아니란 걸 깨달으면
당신을 미워할 거요
We're not talking artists, George,
we're talking freethinkers.
예술가가 아니라
자유로운 사색가가 되라는 거죠
17살의 자유로운 사색가라?
Freethinkers at 17?
비꼬고 계시는 군요?
Funny. l never pegged you
as a cynic.
비꼬는 게 아니라 현실적으로
말하는 겁니다
Not a cynic.
A realist.
Show me the heart
unfettered by foolish dreams...
몽상으로 자유로운 영혼을
보여준다면 나는 만족할 거요
and l'll show you a happy man.
'하지만 진정한 자유란 그들의
꿈에서만 가능합니다'
But only in their dreams
can men be truly free.
'항상 그러했고 항상 그럴 것
입니다'
'Twas always thus,
and always thus will be.
테니슨 시인가요?
Tennyson?
아니요, 자작십니다
No. Keating.
애들아, 도서관에서 선생님의
졸업앨범을 찾아냈어, 봐 봐
Hey, l found his senior annual
in the library.
Listen to this. Captain of the soccer
team, editor of the school annual,
Cambridge bound...
축구 주장, 와!
연감 편집부장, 캠브리지대학
입학 예정
여자 각선미, 죽은시인의 사회
thigh man,
and the Dead Poets Society.
"Man most likely to do anything."
뭐든지 할 수 있는 남자
Thigh man!
Mr. K was a hell-raiser.
각선미를 좋아한다구?
말썽 꾸러기였군
죽은 시인의 사회가 뭐지?
- What's the Dead Poets Society?
- l don't know.
졸업 앨범에 아무런
사진도 언급도 없어
- ls there a picture in the annual?
- No.
- Nothing. No other mention of it.
That boy there, see me after lunch.
거기 학생들! 식사 후
교장실로 오도록!
Mr. Keating?
키팅 선생님? 키팅 선생님?
Mr. Keating!
선생님? 오, 선장님
나의 선장님?
- Sir?
- Say something.
O Captain, my Captain?
날 불렀나?
Gentlemen.
선생님의 졸업 앨범을 봤어요
We were just looking
in your old annual.
오, 이런 이건 내가 아냐
Oh, my God.
No, that's not me.
Stanley "The Tool" Wilson.
스탠리 윌슨, 이런
- God.
- What was the Dead Poets Society?
죽은 시인의 사회가 뭐죠?
l doubt the present administration
would look too favorably upon that.
현재 학교 당국은 절대로
용납하지 않을 걸세
Why? What was it?
왜죠? 그게 뭐였죠?
Gentlemen, can you keep a secret?
비밀로 해줄 수 있겠나?
Sure, yeah.
물론이죠
The Dead Poets were dedicated
to "sucking the marrow out of life."
죽은 시인의 사회는 시의
정수를 빨아들였지
쏘로우 시에서 따온 건데 회합
때마다 그걸 읽곤 했지
That's a phrase from Thoreau
we would invoke
at the beginning of every meeting.
우린 오래된 인디안 동굴에
모여서 차례대로 쏘로우
You see, we would gather
at the old lndian cave...
and take turns reading from Thoreau,
Whitman, Shelley.
휘트만, 셀리같은 위대한 시인의
시를 낭송했어
The biggies!
Even some of our own verse.
우리 자작시도 함께...
And in the enchantment of the moment,
we'd let poetry work its magic.
환희로 모두 시의 마법에
걸린 기분이었지
함께 앉아서 시를 낭송했던
남자들 모임이었단 말인 가요?
You mean, it was a bunch of guys
sitting around reading poetry?
아니야, 오버스트리트군.
남자들만 있었던게 아니야
No, Mr. Overstreet,
it wasn't just guys.
우린 남자들만의 모임이 아니라
낭만주의자들의 모임이었어
We weren't a Greek organization.
We were Romantics.
시만 낭송했던 것이 아니라
시가 꿀처럼 흘러나왔던 거였어
We didn't just read poetry, we let it
drip from our tongues like honey.
영혼이 흘러나왔고 여자들은
황홀했고 신들이 창조되었지
Spirits soared,
women swooned...
and gods were created, gentlemen.
그렇게 저녁을 보내는게
멋있지 않겠어?
Not a bad way to spend an evening, eh?
Thank you, Mr. Perry,
for this stroll down Amnesia Lane.
옛 추억을 되살려 줘서 고맙네
페리군
Burn that, especially my picture.
태워버리게, 특히 내 사진을
Dead Poets Society.
죽은 시인의 사회
뭐?
What?
오늘밤에 가자
- l say we go tonight.
- Tonight?
- Now wait a minute.
- 오늘 밤? 잠깐?
- 모두 갈 거지?
Everybody in?
그 동굴은 어디 있지?
- Where's this cave he's talking about?
- lt's beyond the stream.
l know where it is.
- 강건너에 있어 내가 알아
- 너무 멀잖아
That's miles!
- 난 별로 관심 없어
- 그럼 오지마
- Sounds boring to me.
- Don't come.
- 규율을 어겨 감점당할거야
- 그럼 제발 오지마
- Do you know how many demerits
we're talking, Dalton?
- So don't come. Please.
내 말은 우리 모두 조심해야
된다는 거야, 잡히면 큰일난다구
Look, all l'm saying
is that we have to be careful.
- We can't get caught.
- No shit, Sherlock.
뻔한 말을 하는군
You boys there, hurry up!
거기 학생들! 서둘러!
좋았어, 갈 사람!
All right. Who's in?
닐, 교장이 보이잖아...
- Oh, come on, Neil, Hager's the--
- Forget Hager! No. Who's in?
신경 쓰지마, 올 사람?
난 갈 거야
l'm in.
경고한다, 빨리 들어와!
- l'm warning you! Move!
- Me, too.
나도
난 잘 모르겠어
- l don't know, Neil.
- What? Pitts!
왜? 핏츠
핏츠, 왜 그래
- Pittsie, come on!
- His grades are hurting, Charlie.
성적이 떨어졌잖아
도와줘, 믹스
- You can help him, Meeks.
- What is this? A midnight study group?
이런 밤중의 모임으로?
- 핏츠, 너는 오게 될 거야
- 믹스, 너도 성적이 떨어졌잖아?
Forget it, Pitts, you're coming.
Meeks, your grades hurting, too?
- 난 뭐든지 한번은 해볼 거야
- 성관계만 빼고, 하하하
- l'll try anything once.
- Except sex.
l'm in as long as we're careful.
- 조심만 한다면 갈게, 녹스 넌?
- 모르겠어
- What about you, Knox?
- l don't know, Charlie.
녹스, 크리스를 사귀는데
도움이 될 거야
Come on, Knox,
it'll help you get Chris.
그래? 어떻게?
Yeah? How?
여자들은 황홀했도다
Women swoon!
하지만 왜 황홀해 하지? 찰리
왜 황홀해 하는지 알려줘
But why do they swoon? Charlie,
tell me why they swoon. Charlie!
You're not listening.
Any questions?
핏츠, 잘 들어, 질문 있는 사람?
좋았어, 폭포까지 거슬러 가자
Look, you follow the stream
to the waterfall.
그래 바로 여기야, 여기 위쪽
어딘가 있을 거야
lt's right there.
lt's gotta be like that--
모르겠어, 위험할 것 같아
l don't know.
lt's starting to sound dangerous.
- Oh. Why don't you just stay home?
- Hey, you're crazy.
그럼 오지마
뭐? 정신 나갔니?
For God's sake,
stop chattering and sit down!
자, 잡담 그만하고 제자리에 앉아
토드, 오늘밤에 올 거지?
- Todd, are you coming tonight?
- No.
아니
왜? 키팅 선생님 얘기 들었잖아?
그런 것 해보고 싶지 않니?
Why not? God, you were there.
You heard Keating.
Don't you want to do something about--
Y-Yes. But--
그래, 하지만....
하지만 뭐?
But, but what?
Keating said that everybody
took turns reading and...
키팅 선생님이 모두가 돌아가며
시를 낭송한다고 했는데
난 그렇게 하고 싶지 않아
l don't want to do that.
맙소사, 정말 그게
문제라는 거야?
Gosh. You really have a problem
with that, don't you?
아니, 아니, 문제는 없어 그냥,
하고 싶지 않을 뿐이야, 됐니?
N-No, l, l don't have a problem.
Neil, l just--
l don't want to do it, okay?
All right.
좋아, 읽지 않아도 된다면
어떡할거야?
What if you didn't have to read?
What if you just came and listened?
그냥 와서 듣기만 해도 된다면?
하지만 그런 게 아니잖아
- T-That's not how it works.
- Forget how it works!
그 점은 염려마, 다른 애들이
괜찮다고 한다면 어쩔 거야?
What if-- What if they said
it was okay?
뭐? 애들한테 물어볼거야?
안돼, 안돼, 닐
What? What, are you
gonna go up and ask 'em if--
- No, no.
- l'll be right back.
금방 돌아올게
안돼, 닐
Neil? Neil?
조용히 해
Oh, shut up, will you?
lt's my stuff for my asthma, okay?
Could you give that back, please?
그건..... 내 천식 약이야
알았어? 어서 돌려줘!
- Could you give that back?
- What's the matter?
Don't you like snakes?
너도 가는 거야
- You're in.
- Get away from me, okay?
저리 떨어져
스팟, 주머니 안에 보지 그래?
Spaz, why don't you check
your pockets?
- Come on, Spaz,
l have to brush my teeth.
- Hurry up. Get off.
소란 피우지 마라
Cut out that racket in there.
- Come on. Let's get out.
- Go! Go!
야!!!! 난 죽은 시인이다!
l'm a dead poet!
- Charlie.
- Guys, over here!
- 쉬! 얘들아! 이쪽이야!
- 잘났다, 정말 잘났어
You're funny. You're real funny.
lt's too wet.
너무 축축한데
맙소사, 연기 피워서 다 질식
시킬 셈이야?
God, you trying
to smoke us out of here?
아니야, 연기는 이쪽으로 다
빠져 나간다구
No, no, the smoke's
going right up this opening.
You okay?
괜찮아?
Oh, God. Clods.
됐어, 모닥불은 그만 두자
- All right, all right, forget the fire.
- Forget it, forget it.
그래, 그만 둬
자, 시작하자, 이제 죽은 시인의
사회 재결성을 선언하다
- Let's go, gentlemen.
- Can't light a swamp.
l hereby reconvene
the Dead Poets Society.
Welton Chapter. The, uh, meetings
will be conducted by myself
and the other new initiates now present.
이 모임의 회원은 나와 오늘
모인 사람들이다
Uh, Todd Anderson,
because he prefers not to read,
will keep the minutes of the meetings.
토드 앤더슨은 낭송을 하지
않기 때문에 서기 일을 맡는다
l'll now read the traditional
opening message...
이제 헨리 D. 쏘로우의 전통적인
개회 시구를 낭송하겠다
by society member
Henry David Thoreau.
'나는 자유롭게 살기 위해
숲속에 왔다'
"l went to the woods because
l wanted to live deliberately.
'삶의 정수를 빨아들이기 위해
사려 깊게 살고 싶다'
l wanted to live deep,
and suck out all the marrow of life."
동의합니다
l'll second that.
"To put to rout all that was not life...
'삶이 아닌 것을 모두 떨치고
삶이 다했을 때 삶에 대해
후회하지 말라'
and not, when l had come to die,
discover that l had not lived."
그리고, 어, 키팅 선생님이
잔뜩 표시를 해 뒀어
And, uh, Keating's marked
a bunch of other pages.
자, 휴식이다.
여기 전부 쏟아 놔
All right, intermission. Dig deep.
Right here, right here, lay it down.
진흙 위에? 무슨 소리야
On the mud?
We're gonna put our food on the mud?
Meeks, put your coat down.
Picnic blanket.
믹스, 네 코트를 위에다 깔아
어서 깔아
- Yes, sir!
- Excuse me.
- Use Meeks' coat.
항상 내 옷이군
하나도 숨기지 말고 다 꺼내
너희들은 항상 담배만 피우더라
Don't keep anything back, either.
You guys are always bumming my smokes.
건포도?
- Raisins?
- Yeah.
그래
잠깐! 누가 빵을 반쪽만
내논거야?
Wait a minute.
Who gave us half a roll?
반쪽은 내가 먹고 있어
- l'm eating the other half.
- Come on!
그러지마!
What? You want me to put it back?
뭐, 먹다만 것을 내놓으란 거야?
lt was a dark and rainy night.
어둠이 내리고 비가 내리던 밤에
And this old lady,
who had a passion for jigsaw puzzles...
조각그림 맞추기를 좋아 하던
할머니가
새 조각 그림을 맞추려고
책상 앞에 앉았어
sat by herself in her house at her table
to complete the new jigsaw puzzle.
As she pieced the puzzle together...
하지만 맞추기가 끝나 갈
즈음에 할머니는 깜짝 놀랐어
she realized to her astonishment...
그녀가 맞춘 그림은 그녀의
방과 아주 똑같았고
that the image that was formed
was her very own room...
가운데 써 있는 그림은 자신과
똑같았지
and the figure in the center of the
puzzle as she completed it was herself.
And with trembling hands,
she placed the last four pieces...
떨리는 손으로 마지막 네
조각을 끼워 넣자
and stared in horror at the face
of a demented madman at the window.
창문에 비친, 미친 남자
얼굴을 보게 됐어
할머니는 창문 깨지는 소리를
마지막으로 들었지
The last thing that this old lady ever
heard was the sound of breaking glass.
- No shit.
- Yes. This is true. This is true.
이건 실화야, 실화라구
l've got one that's even
better than that. l do.
넌 더 좋은 얘기가 있어
젊은 부부 하나가 밤중에
숲속을 차로 지나가다가
There's a young married couple
and they're driving through the forest
at night from a long trip.
기름이 떨어졌어
And they run out of gas,
and there's a madman on the loose.
그런데 그곳에 미친 남자가...
- Oh, that thing with the hand?
- This is the madman on the roof?
손이 달린 얘기 말이지?
- l love that story.
- l told you that one.
그 얘기 좋아!
내가 해준 얘기잖아
- You did not. l got that in,
uh, camp in sixth grade.
- Yeah. Were you six last year?
아니야, 6학년때 캠프에서
들은 얘기야
'옛날 옛날에 윌릴 플로트라는
남자가 살고 있었다
"ln a mean abode in the Shankill Road
lived a man named William Bloat.
Now he had a wife,
the plague of his life...
그에겐 부인이 있었는데 아주
골치덩어리였어
항상 그를 괴롭혔거든
who continually got his goat.
그러던 어느 날 새벽, 잠자던
아내의 목을 베어 버렸다
And one day at dawn
with her night shift on...
he slit her bloody throat."
이런, 갈수록 태산이군
- Oh, and it gets worse.
- Do you wanna hear a real poem?
진짜 시를 들어볼래?
자, 여기 있어
- Want this?
- All right? No, l don't need it.
You take it.
필요 없어. 들고 있어
또 가져왔니?
- What, did you bring one?
- You memorized a poem?
시를 외워 버렸다고?
외워버렸다구?
l didn't memorize a poem.
Move up.
일어나, 찰리 달튼의 자작시지
아주 독창적인 거지
- An original piece by Charlie Dalton.
- An original piece.
- 우, 중앙에 서
- 이봐, 이건 역사야
- Take center stage.
- You know this is history.
Right? This is history.
- Oh, wow.
- Where did you get that?
어디서 구했지?
- Whoa.
'사랑을 가르쳐 준다고?
"Teach me to love?
가서 더 재주를 배우고 오너라
난 이 분야의 대가이다
Go teach thyself more wit.
l, chief professor, am of it.
사랑의 신이 있다고 하더라도
나한테 더 배워야 할거다
The god of love,
if such a thing there be...
may learn to love from me."
Wow! Did you write that?
와, 네게 쓴 거야?
애브라함 카울리
자, 다음은 누구지?
Abraham Cowley.
Okay, who's next?
Alfred Lord Tennyson.
알프레드 테니슨경 '친구들이여
내게 오라
"Come, my friends.
신세계를 찾는데 늦지 않았도다
'Tis not too late
to seek a newer world.
내 결심은 확고하니
석양 너머로 항해하자
For my purpose holds
to sail beyond the sunset.
천지를 움직였던 옛적의 힘은
지금 없을지라도
And though we are not now
that strength which in old days...
moved earth and heaven...
우리는 아직도 영웅적 마음의
기질은 있도다
that which we are, we are.
One equal temper of heroic hearts...
운명과 시간으로 약해졌어도
의지는 강하도다
made weak by time and fate,
but strong in will.
갈망하고 추구하고 굴복하지
않도다
To strive, to seek, to find...
and not to yield."
"Then l had religion.
Then l had a vision.
그때 나는 종교를 가졌고 난
조롱 속에 있었네
l could not turn from
their revel in derision.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track."
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
- Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
- Meeks. Meeks.
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black...
황금의 통로가 숲속을 가로지르네
cutting through the forest
with a golden track.
그때 난 어둠 속에 나타난
콩고를 보았네
Then l saw the Congo
creeping through the black--
A man is not very tired.
He is exhausted!
매우 지쳤다, 대신에 녹초가
되었다 하고
And don't use, "very sad."
Use--
매우 슬프다 대신에......
멍청이 오버스트릿트군
Come on, Mr. Overstreet, you twerp.
비통하다?
- Morose?
- Exactly! Morose.
그렇지, 비통하다야, 언어가
발명된 이유가 뭐지?
Now, language was developed for one
endeavor, and that is? Mr. Anderson?
앤더슨군? 자, 말해봐
자네는 용기가 없나?
Come on!
Are you a man or an amoeba?
페리군
Mr. Perry?
언어 소통을 위해서요
Uh, to communicate.
No! To woo women.
아니야! 여자를 꼬시기 위해서야!
오늘 우린 세익스피어의
시를 배우도록 하겠다
Today we're going to be talking
about William Shakespeare.
Oh, God!
모두 들 치과에 가는 것처럼
싫어한다는 것을 알고 있다
l know. A lot of you look forward
to this about as much
as you look forward to root canal work.
하지만 세익스피어가 정말
재미있는 작가임을 알게 될 거다
We're gonna talk about Shakespeare
as someone who writes something
very interesting.
Now, many of you have seen
Shakespeare done very much like this.
세익스피어가 이런 말을 한 것을
들은 적이 있을 거야
'오, 타이터스야 네 친구를
이리 데려오너라'
"O Titus, bring your friend hither."
But if any of you have seen
Mr. Marlon Brando...
하지만 만약 말론 브란도가
세익스피어가 한 말을 한다면
달라지겠지
you know Shakespeare can be different.
"Friends, Romans, countrymen,
lend me your ears."
'친구여, 로마인 이여
동포여 내게 귀를 기울여라'
또 존웨인이 맥베스라면
You can also imagine, maybe,
John Wayne as Macbeth going...
'내 앞에 있는 게 단검인가?'
"Well, is this a dagger
l see before me?"
"Dogs, sir?
Oh, not just now.
'개라고? 오, 지금은 아니야
l do enjoy a good dog
once in a while, sir.
저도 가끔은 개를 먹죠
개 한 마리라면 한끼를
잘 먹을 수 있죠
You can have yourself
a three-course meal from one dog.
개 크로켓을 먹고 주식은
플랑베를 들고
Start with your canine crudites...
go to your Fido flambe
for main course...
and for dessert,
a Pekingese parfait.
후식은 북경개 파르페죠
And you can pick your teeth
with a little paw."
그리고 발톱으론
이빨을 쑤십니다
Why do l stand up here?
Anybody?
내가 왜 이 위에 섰는지
이유를 아는 사람?
- 크다는 기분을 알려고요
- 아니야, 다음 기회로 모시겠소
- To feel taller.
- No! Thank you for playing, Mr. Dalton.
l stand upon my desk
to remind myself...
이 위에 선 이유는 사물을
that we must constantly look at things
in a different way.
다른 각도에서 보려는 거야
이 위에서 보면 세상이 무척
다르게 보이지
You see, the world looks
very different from up here.
믿기지 않는다면 너희들도
한 번 해봐, 어서, 어서
You don't believe me?
Come see for yourselves. Come on.
Come on!
Just when you think you know something,
you have to look at it in another way.
어떤 사실을 안다고 생각할 땐
그것을 다른 시각에서 봐라
Even though it may seem silly
or wrong, you must try!
틀리고 바보 같은 일일 지라도
시도를 해봐야 해
책을 읽을 때 저자의 생각만
고려하지 말고
Now, when you read, don't just consider
what the author thinks...
너희들의 생각도
고려해 보도록 해
consider what you think.
Boys, you must strive to find
your own voice.
너희들의 목소리를 찾을 수
있도록 투쟁해야 해
늦게 시작할수록 찾기가 더
힘들 것이다
Because the longer you wait to begin,
the less likely you are
to find it at all.
Thoreau said, "Most men lead lives
of quiet desperation."
쏘로우는 '대부분의 사람들이
절망적으로 산다고 했다'
그렇게 물러나지 마라
Don't be resigned to that.
Break out!
내려와, 그냥 그렇게 가장 자리만
빙빙 돌지만 말고 주위를 둘러봐라
Don't just walk off the edge
like lemmings. Look around you.
There! There you go, Mr. Priske.
Thank you! Yes!
잘했다, 프리스키군, 고맙다
그거야
과감하게 부딪쳐 새로운
세계를 찾아라
Dare to strike out
and find new ground.
레포트와 함께 자작시
한 편 씩을
Now, in addition to your essays,
l would like you to compose a poem
of your own, an original work.
지어 오도록
그렇지
That's right! You have to deliver it
aloud in front of the class on Monday.
월요일 수업에는 각자의 시를
직접 낭독하도록 한다
행운을 비네
Bon chance, gentlemen.
앤더슨 군
Mr. Anderson?
Don't think that l don't know that this
assignment scares the hell out of you,
you mole.
이 숙제를 겁내고 있다는 거
알아, 이 두더지 같은 친구
Take a power train in two!
2번을 반복해서 힘차게 저어라
3번, 똑바로 못하니
- Three!
- Stroke, stroke.
- Keep your eyes in the boat!
We got it, Pittsie, we got it!
됐어, 됐다구
드디어 방송이 잡혔어
Radio Free America!
Some people like to rock
Some people like to roll
But movin' and a-groovin's
gonna satisfy my soul
Let's have a party
Ooh
Let's send it to the soul
Let's rock and roll
Let's have a party tonight
l never kissed a bear
l never kissed a goose
But l can shake a chicken
in the middle of the room
Let's have a party
- 찾았어
- 뭘 찾았다는 거야?
- l found it!
- You found what?
지금 내가 정말, 정말로
하고 싶은 일을 찾았단 말야
What l want to do right now.
What's really, really inside of me.
- '한 여름밤의 꿈' 이거야?
- 맞아
- A Midsummer Night's Dream?
- This is it.
- What is that?
- 그게 뭔데?
- 연극이잖아
- lt's a play, dummy.
- l know that.
그건 알아
l-- Wh-Wh--What does
it have to do with you?
그, 그게 너와 무슨 상관이지?
그래, 헨리홀에서 공연할건데
오디션을 할거래
Right. They're putting it on at
Henley Hall. Open tryouts. Open tryouts!
- 공개오디션을 한다구
- 그래서?
- Yes, so?
- So...
그래서! 연극을 해볼 거야!
그래!그래! 배우가 될 거야!
l'm gonna act.
Yes, yes!
l'm gonna be an actor!
난 항상 연극을 하고 싶었어
Ever since l can remember,
l've wanted to try this.
지난 여름 오디션에도 나가려
했는데 아버지가 반대했어
l even tried to go
to summer stock auditions last year...
but, of course,
my father wouldn't let me.
내 인생 처음으로, 난 내가
뭘하고 싶은지를 알아냈어
For the first time in my whole life,
l know what l want to do.
그리고 처음으로 아버지가
And, for the first time, l'm gonna do it
whether my father wants me to or not!
찬성하든 말든 난 내가 하고
싶은 것을 할거야! 카르페 디엠!
Carpe diem!
닐, 닐, 진정해 아버지가 승락하지
않으면 어떻게 할거야?
Neil, Neil, hold on a minute.
How are you gonna be in a play
if your father won't let you?
First l gotta get the part.
Then l can worry about that.
배역을 따고 볼 거야
걱정은 다음에 하지
어쩌면 널 죽이려고 하실텐데
말씀도 안드렸다는걸 아신다면
Yeah, but won't he kill you
if he finds out you went to an audition
and didn't even tell him?
No, no, no, no. As far as l'm concerned,
he won't have to know about any of this.
아냐, 아냐,
아버지는 아실 필요가 없어
- Well, that's impossible.
- Bullshit! Nothing's impossible.
그건 불가능해
웃기지마 불가능은 없어
Well, why don't you just call him
and ask him? And m-maybe he'll say yes.
이봐, 전화해서 말해봐
허락을 하실지 누가 아니?
That's a laugh!
말도 안돼, 말씀 안 드린다고 해도
아버지를 거역하는 건아냐
lf l don't ask him,
at least l won't be disobeying him.
그래, 하지만...
- Yeah, but if he said--
- Jesus, Todd! Whose side are you on?
제길, 토드, 너 누구 편이야?
아직 배역도 안 땄지만
l mean, l haven't even gotten
the part yet.
생각만, 그냥 생각만 해도
기분이 좋다구
Can't l even en-enjoy the idea
for a little while?
You're coming to the meeting
this afternoon?
- 오늘 오후 모임에 올 거지?
- 확실히 모르겠어
l don't know. Maybe.
키팅 선생님의 말을 이해못하
는건 아니겠지
Nothing Mr. Keating has to say
means shit to you, does it, Todd?
- W-What is that supposed to mean?
- You're in the club!
그, 그게 무슨 뜻이야?
우리 모임의 회원이라면..
반응을 보여야 하는데
Being in the club means
being stirred up by things.
넌 전혀 동요가 없다구
- You look about as stirred up
as a cesspool.
- S-- You want me out?
나보고 빠지라는 거야?
아냐. 난 네가 있었으면 해, 하지만
회원인 이상 너도 뭔가를
No! l want you in! But being in
means you gotta do something,
not just say you're in.
해야 한다구 그냥 말로서만
회원이 아니라
닐, 네 마음을 이해하지만, 난
너하고 달라, 알겠니?
Well, listen, Neil, l, l appreciate
this concern, but l-l'm not like you.
All right? You, you--
You say things and people listen.
어, 네, 네가 말하면 사람들이
귀기울여 들어주지만
나, 난, 아니라구
- Uh, l'm, l'm not like that.
- Don't you think you could be?
너도 그렇게 할 수 있다고는
생각지 않아?
No! l-- l, l don't know,
but that's not the point.
안돼.....모르겠어
하지만 문제는 그게 아냐
The, the point is that
there's nothing you can do about it,
so you can just butt out.
중요한 건 네가 어쩔수 없는
일이니까
그냥 날 내버려 두라고
내 자신은 내가 돌볼 테니까
알겠어?
l can take care of myself just fine.
All right?
No.
아니
아니라니 무슨 뜻이지?
What do you mean "no"?
아니
No.
그거 내놔, 닐! 어서 돌려 달라구!
- Give me-- Neil. Neil, give that back.
- "We are dreaming of a--"
'우린 꿈꾸고 있다....' 뭐야?
시잖아, 휘트먼이 날 i고있다
Poetry! l'm being chased
by Walt Whitman!
- 알았어! 알았다구! 카메론!
- 너희들 뭐해?
Okay, okay.
What are you guys doing?
l'm sure-- You see this chemistry--
난 지금 화학공부 하고 있는데
어서 내 책 내놔, 닐
Hey, give me-- Neil, give me--
Don't be immature. Come on.
l need my--
어서 달라구, 어린애처럼
그러지 말라구. 빨리 내....
나한테 줘, 나한테
- Give it to me! Give it to me!
- Charlie, help me.
어서 돌려줘
Okay, everybody on the bus.
자, 모두 버스에 타
어서 버스에 타
Let's go, boys.
Come on, let's go.
On the bus, boys.
어서 타!
Now!
Now, devotees may argue
that one sport or game
is inherently better than another.
스포츠 팬은 어떤 경기종목이
좋다 나쁘다 논쟁할 수 있지만
For me, sport is actually
a chance for us to have
other human beings push us to excel.
나에게 스포츠란 우리가 타인보다
탁월함을 보여주는 기회라고
생각한다
l want you all to come over here
and take a slip of paper...
자, 모두 여기에 와서 쪽지를
하나씩 가지고
일렬종대로 줄을 서라
and line up single file.
Mr. Meeks, time to inherit the earth.
믹스, 땅을 물려줘라
핏츠, 이름 보다는 잘해라
애들에게 한 장씩 나눠줘라
Mr. Pitts, rise above your name.
l want you to hand these out
to the boys, one apiece.
어떻게 하는지 알지, 핏츠
You know what to do, Pitts.
'승산 없는 싸움에 도전
겁없는 적을 상대하기 위해'
"Oh, to struggle against great odds.
To meet enemies undaunted."
겁에 질린 목소린데, 다시
겁없는 목소리로 해봐
Sounds to me like you're daunted.
Say it again like you're undaunted.
승산 없는 싸움에 도전, 겁없는
적을 상대하기 위해
"Oh, to struggle against great odds.
To meet enemies undaunted."
자, 공을 차
좋아, 다음
Now go on.
Yes! Next.
"To be a sailor of the world,
bound for all ports."
'세계의 모든 항구를 구경할
선원이 되기 위하여'
다음, 더 크게
Next. Louder!
'오, 난 인생의 노예가 아닌
지배자가 되기 위해 산다'
"Oh, l live to be the ruler of life,
not a slave."
"To mount the scaffolds.
To advance to the muzzles of guns
with perfect nonchalance."
'사형 대에 처해지기 위해
총구 앞에서 태연하게
전진할 수 있게 하기 위하여
Come on, Meeks!
Listen to the music.
자, 음악을 들어라, 믹스
춤추고 손뼉치며, 기쁘고
뛰고 소리치고 떠다니기 위하여
"To dance, clap hands...
exalt, shout, skip,
roll on, float on."
다음
Yes!
오, 지금부터 새롭고 즐거운
시와 인생을 갖기 위하여
"Oh, to have life henceforth
the poem of new joys."
Oh! Boo!
오! 부! 힘내라 찰리! 있는
힘을 다해라!
Come on, Charlie,
let it fill your soul!
"To indeed be a god!"
'참된 신이 되기 위하여!
Charlie! l got the part!
찰리, 나 배역을 땄어
내가 퍽을 맡게 됐어
퍽을 맡게 됐어
l'm gonna play Puck!
뭐라고 했지? 엿먹어라!
- What did he say?
- Puck? Yes.
- That's the main part.
- Great, Neil.
시끄러! 주연을 맡았어!
멋지다, 닐! 찰리, 나 해냈어
- Charlie, l got it!
- Congratulations.
- Good for you, Neil. Good for you.
축하해, 닐
좋겠다, 닐
자, 진정하고...
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
닐, 이제 어떻게 할거야?
Neil, how are you gonna do this?
아버지와 교장선생님의
허가서가 필요해
They need a letter of permission
from my father and Mr. Nolan.
설마, 네가 작성할거니?
- You're not gonna write it.
- Oh, yes, l am.
- 그래, 내가 할거야
- 오, 닐, 제정신이야?
Oh, Neil-- Neil, you're crazy.
Okay. "l am writing to you...
됐어, '내 아들을 대신해서
편지를 씁니다.'
on behalf of...
my son...
Neil Perry."
닐 페리
끝내준다
This is great.
'크리스에게'
"To Chris."
- Who's Chris?
- Mmm, Chris.
ㅇ
음
그녀의 미소에는 달콤함이 있네
"l see a sweetness in her smile.
그녀의 눈에서 빛나는
밝은 빛이여
Bright light shines from her eyes.
하지만 인생은 완벽하네
내 인생은 완전하다네
But life is complete,
contentment is mine...
그녀가....
just knowing that--"
"Just knowing that...
그녀가 살아있다는 것을
아는 것 만으로도
she's alive."
죄송합니다, 엉터리입니다
- Sorry, Captain. lt's stupid.
- No, no, it's not stupid.
아니야, 엉터리가 아냐
열심히 했어, 중요한 주제 가운데
하나인 사랑을 다뤘어
lt's a good effort. lt touched on one
of the major themes: love.
A major theme not only in poetry,
but life.
시뿐만 아니라 인생에 있어서도
중요한 주제지
Mr. Hopkins, you were laughing.
홉킨스, 자네가 웃었으니까
자네가 해봐
You're up.
'고양이가 매트 위에 앉았네'
"The cat sat on the mat."
축하하네, 홉킨스
Congratulations, Mr. Hopkins.
Yours is the first poem...
프리차드 채점의 첫 마이너스
점수를 냈네
to ever have a negative score
on the Pritchard scale.
자넬 비웃는 것이 아니라
자네와 함께 비웃었어
We're not laughing at you,
we're laughing near you.
주제가 간단하다고 해도
문제 될건 없다
l don't mind that your poem
had a simple theme. Sometimes
the most beautiful poetry...
때론 가장 아름다운 시란
can be about simple things,
like a cat, or a flower or rain.
단순한 주제에 관한 것일 수
있으니까, 고양이나 꽃
아니면 비같은 걸로, 시는 계시를
지니고 어디서나 우러 나오지
You see, poetry can come from anything
with the stuff of revelation in it.
평범하게는 쓰지 말아라
Just don't let your poems
be ordinary.
자, 다음은 누가 할까?
Now, who's next?
앤더슨 군, 자네는 거기 앉아서
고뇌에 차있군
Mr. Anderson,
l see you sitting there in agony.
Come on, Todd, step up.
Let's put you out of your misery.
자, 토드군 앞으로 나오게
자네 문제를 해결해 주겠네
전, 전, 시를 안 썼어요
l, l didn't do it.
l didn't write a poem.
앤더슨군은 자신의 내면에 있는
것은 모두 가치 없고
Mr. Anderson thinks that everything
inside of him is worthless...
수치스럽 게 보는군
and embarrassing.
안 그런가? 그게 네 두려움이야
난 네가 잘못됐다고 생각한다
lsn't that right, Todd?
lsn't that your worst fear?
Well, l think you're wrong. l think
you have something inside of you...
네 내면에는 매우 가치있는게
들어있다
that is worth a great deal.
내 야성을 지르노라'
"l sound...
my barbaric...
yawp...
over the rooftops...
'나는 이 세상 지붕 꼭대기에서
of the world."
다시 휘트먼 아저씨 말이야
W.W. Uncle Walt again.
자, 여기서 야성이란 커다란 울부
짖음이다
Now, for those of you who don't know,
a yawp is a loud cry or yell.
자, 토드군, 이리 나와서 우리
에게 야성이 무엇인지를 보여주게
Now, Todd, l would like you to give us
a demonstration of a barbaric "yawp."
Come on. You can't yawp sitting down.
Let's go. Come on. Up.
어서, 앉아서는 야성을 보여줄
수 없지, 일어서, 어서 앞으로 나와
야성 자세를 취해라
You gotta get in "yawping" stance.
어, 야
- A, a yawp.
- No, not just a yawp. A barbaric yawp.
그냥 야가 아니라 야성을
내라니까
야
- Yawp.
- Come on, louder.
- 더 크게
- 야
- Yawp.
- No, that's a mouse. Come on. Louder.
- 쥐새끼 소리만 하다 더 크게 해
- 야
- Yawp.
- Oh, good God, boy, yell like a man!
- Yawp!
- 이런, 더 사나이답게
- 야!
바로 그거야, 네 내면에도
야성스러운 면이 있어
There it is. You see, you have
a barbarian in you after all.
Now, you don't get away
that easy.
벌써 들어가면 안되지, 저기
휘트먼 아저씨의 사진이 있다
That picture of Uncle Walt up there.
What does he remind you of?
Don't think. Answer. Go on.
저 사진이 뭘 연상시키나 말해봐
생각하지 말고 그냥 말해
미친 사람
- A m-m-madman.
- What kind of madman?
어떤 종류의 미친 사람?
생각나는 대로 대답해
- Don't think about it.
Just answer again.
- A c-crazy madman.
정신나간 미친 사람
No, you can do better than that.
Free up your mind. Use your imagination.
오, 더 나아지는군
마음을 열고 상상력을 펼치고
Say the first thing that pops into your
head, even if it's total gibberish.
머릿속에 퍼뜩 떠오르는걸 얘기해
바보 같은 얘기 라도 좋아
- Go on, go on.
- Uh, uh, a sweaty-toothed madman.
땀에 젖어 이를 드러낸 사람
좋아, 잘했어, 너한테도 시적
인게 있구나!
Good God, boy, there's a poet
in you after all.
자, 이번엔 눈을
감아, 눈을 감아
There, close your eyes.
Close your eyes. Close 'em.
눈을 감아, 감고 뭐가 보이는지
말해라
Now, describe what you see.
- Uh, l, l close my eyes.
- Yes?
눈을 감았습니다
그리고?
- 그의 모습이 내게로 와요
- 땀에 젖고 이를 드러낸 그가
- Uh, and this image floats beside me.
- A sweaty-toothed madman?
땀에 젖고 이를 드러낸 그가
나의 뇌를 노려보고 있어요
A sweaty-toothed madman
with a stare that pounds my brain.
오, 훌륭해, 그에게 뭔가를
시켜봐, 뭔가를 시켜보라구
Oh, that's excellent. Now, give him
action. Make him do something.
그의 손이 뻗어와서 내 목을
잡아요
- H-His hands reach out and choke me.
- That's it. Wonderful. Wonderful.
그렇지, 훌륭해
계속 뭔가를 중얼거립니다
- And, and all the time he's mumbling.
- What's he mumbling?
뭘 중얼거리고 있지?
M-Mumbling, "Truth. Truth, like,
like a blanket that always
leaves your feet cold."
- 진실을 중얼거리고 있어요
- 그래
진실은 발을 차갑게 하는
이불 같은 것입니다
무시하고 신경 쓰지 마
이불 얘기를 계속해봐
Forget them, forget them. Stay with the
blanket. Tell me about that blanket.
Y-Y-Y-- Y-You push it, stretch it,
it'll never be enough.
잡아당겨도 늘어뜨려도
이불은 부족합니다
You kick at it, beat it,
it'll never cover any of us.
무슨 수를 써봐도 이불은
우릴 덮어주질 못합니다
From the moment we enter crying,
to the moment we leave dying...
울면서 태어난 날부터 죽음
으로 떠나는 날까지
울고 절규하고 신음하는 우리의
얼굴만을 덮을 겁니다
it will cover your face
as you wail and cry and scream.
Don't you forget this.
오늘 수업을 기억해라
바로 그거야, 깊게 빨아들여
Attaboy, Pittsie, inhale deeply.
- 우리 아버진 파이프를 수집하셔
- 그래? 난 한 30개쯤 될 거야
- My dad collects a lot of pipes.
- Really? Mine's got 30.
Your parents collect pipes?
Oh, that's really interesting.
파이프를 수집하신다구?
정말 재밌다
Come on, Knox. Join in.
뭐해? 녹스, 너도 피워봐
그래, 녹스, 문제가 있으면
우리한테 얘기해, 도와줄게
- Yeah, Knox, we're from the government.
We're here to help, man.
- What's wrong?
크리스 때문이다, 여기 크리스
사진이 있다, 여기!
- lt's Chris.
- Here's a picture of Chris for you.
피워봐, 파이프에 넣고 피워봐
- Smoke that. Put that in your pipe
and smoke it.
- That's not funny.
그만 놀려
Knock it off.
Smoke your pipes.
그만하고, 파이프 피워
- Neil!
- Friends, scholars, Welton men.
알았어, 닐!
친구여! 학자여! 웰튼인이여!
- What is that, Neil?
- Duh. lt's a lamp, Meeks.
- 그게 뭐니, 닐!
- 바보야, 램프잖아!
- 아니야, 이건 동굴의 신이야
- 동굴의 신?
- No. This is the god of the cave.
- The god of the cave.
- Charlie, what are you doing?
- What do you say we start this meeting?
회합을 시작하도록 하자
- Y-Yeah, just-- l need a light.
l just gotta--
- Got any earplugs?
잠깐....라이터가 필요해
라이터 있는 사람?
귀마개 가지고 왔니?
여러분, 찰스 달톤의
즉흥시 입니다
Gentlemen, "Poetrusic"
by Charles Dalton.
Oh, boy. He's gonna play.
Oh, no.
Laughing, crying, tumbling, mumbling.
웃음, 눈물, 비틀거림
중얼거림은 더 많이 할수록 더
많이 있다, 윽!
Gotta do more. Gotta be more.
혼돈의 고함과 혼돈의 꿈은
많이 할 수록 많이 있다, 와
Chaos screaming, chaos dreaming.
Gotta do more. Gotta be more!